Imagine just leaving your desk for a quick lunch, right?
Yeah, just grabbing a sandwich.
Exactly.
And by the time you get back, your digital intern has not only written 20,000 lines of code,
but it has completely rewritten your company's core database architecture.
Oh, man.
And in the process, it accidentally uploaded your AWS passwords to a malicious server.
It sounds like an absolute nightmare scenario.
But as of March 2026, it's actually entirely possible.
Yeah, it really is.
Welcome to today's deep dive.
Our mission today is to just cut through all the relentless noise of this AI hype cycle
and figure out what is actually changing how developers, entrepreneurs, and creators work.
Because there's a lot of noise right now.
So much noise.
We're looking at a massive stack of the latest briefings today.
We've got stuff from AI power stacks, the rundown AI,
Benzbites, latent space, and Simon Wilson's weblog.
A really solid lineup.
Yeah.
And to you listening to this right now, we are going to extract the practical tools
that are actually worth trying today.
We're going to expose those overlapping subscriptions that are quietly bleeding your wallet dry.
Oh, we all have those.
Right.
And we're going to unpack the hidden dangers of these fully automated workflows.
Because honestly, following AI right now is like trying to drink from a fire hose
while the fire hose is constantly upgrading its own nozzle.
That is exactly what it feels like.
Right.
And to really understand what's happening, we have to establish one core theme for this deep dive.
OK, lay it on us.
We have decisively moved past the era of AI as a chat interface.
Right.
Like chat GPT in a browser window.
Exactly.
That era is over.
We are now firmly in the era of AI as an autonomous agent.
So the goal today is to map out how you can wield this new power
without completely losing control of your own projects.
And you really see this shift just by looking at what the frontier models are doing right now.
The landscape is pivoting hard.
Like incredibly hard from generative novelties to pure executions.
Yeah, the focus is completely shifted.
I mean, look at OpenAI Sora.
They're huge video generator.
It just got the axe completely shelf.
Which was a massive shock to a lot of people.
Right.
But meanwhile, text and reasoning models are just exploding.
GPT 5.4 just dropped with a context window of over one million tokens.
These stagger.
And Claude just solved an open math problem.
So why are these companies dropping the flashy video tools to focus on text and reasoning?
Because the contrast there reveals where the actual value is.
The real return on investment isn't in generating a cinematic video of a cat walking on Mars.
This fun is that is.
Right.
It's fun.
But compute is expensive.
They're routing all their computing power toward what we're calling remote control AI.
Remote control AI.
Okay, let's unpack this.
Because this brings us to what Anthropic just shipped.
They released a feature called dispatch for Claude coworker.
This is a game changer.
It blew my mind.
You can literally message Claude from your phone while you're getting coffee down the street.
And it will execute tasks on your physical desktop computer back at the office.
Just move with the mouse, opening files.
Running scripts, yeah.
And development environments are following suit.
The cursor IDE has officially entered its third era cloud agents.
And they're acquiring tools like graphite and auto tab.
What's fascinating here is that this is the exact same path
meta is taking with their new hyper agents.
The ones that teach themselves how to learn.
Exactly.
The whole shift is moving from creation to pure autonomous execution.
So it's like upgrading from a really smart dictionary to an intern
who literally logs into your laptop while you're out to lunch.
That's a great way to put it.
The human's role is no longer to do the physical work,
but to orchestrate it.
But I have to ask, is handing over the mouse and keyboard actually making us more productive,
or is it just creating massive anxiety?
Well, that brings us to the dual-edge sort of what people are calling vibe coding.
Oh, vibe coding. I love and hate this term.
It's super polarizing, right?
Totally. For those listening who aren't in the trenches with this every day,
vibe coding is basically when you stop writing actual syntax.
You just give the system the general intention,
the vibes of what you want,
and the AI handles all the semicolons and loops.
And the highs of this approach are incredible.
There really are.
Like Simon Wilson notes a team that rewrote the entire Jason Auto expression language,
which is heavy-duty stuff.
It's used in Node Red and things like that.
Right. And they ported it into Go in just one day.
One single day.
Using a shadow deployment and AI.
And they saved $500,000 a year in compute costs.
And Wilson also talks about how fast and fun it is to just vibe codes with UI apps
on the new M5 MacBook Pro.
The velocity is just undeniable.
But we have to talk about the terrifying lows here.
Yeah, the hangover from vibe coding.
Exactly. Mario Zekner, the creator of the Pi Agent Framework,
has this really harsh warning in the sources.
He basically says we need to slow the F down.
Wow.
He calls these agents merchants of complexity.
Merchants of complexity.
Because the human bottleneck is gone, right?
An agent can just, as he puts it,
shit out 20,000 lines of code in a few hours.
And it introduces all these tiny,
innocent-looking mistakes.
Compounding mistakes.
They form an unsustainable monster,
and suddenly your cognitive debt is skyrocketing.
You don't even understand your own software anymore.
Here's where it gets really interesting, though.
I want to push back on that.
I'll for it.
If a company can save half a million dollars in a single afternoon
by vibe-porting Jay Sonata,
isn't that massive cognitive debt completely worth it?
It's attempting trade-off.
I mean, it feels like taking out a high interest loan
to build a skyscraper overnight.
Like, yeah, the interest rate on the technical debt is terrible,
but hey, I have a fully functioning skyscraper tomorrow morning.
I agree.
It's a very real business calculation.
But the problem with the skyscraper analogy,
is that eventually,
you have to pay for the maintenance of a building
you don't even understand.
Ooh, yeah, that's true.
Matt Webb has this great quote in the sources where he says,
agents grind problems to dust.
Grind problems to dust.
Right, they just brute force their way to a solution.
And because they do that architecture matters more than ever,
anything that defines the gestalt of the system,
the core API, the fundamental logic
that still has to be written by hand.
Because if the AI builds a cracked foundation,
the whole thing collapses.
Exactly.
And moving this fast doesn't just create messy code.
It creates massive financial and security blind spots.
And these blind spots are being exploited right now.
This is where things get genuinely scary.
Let's talk about the real cost of this stuff.
First, the financial waste.
The average developer is now spending
over $100 a month on AI tools.
They're burning cash on subscriptions.
So much redundant overlap.
But that's nothing compared to the security nightmare.
We have to talk about the LIDALM supply chain
at pack on PIPI.
Yes, this is a perfect example
of what goes wrong when agents move too fast.
So version 1.82.8 of LIDALM contained a credential stealer.
It was hidden in base 64 within a file
called LIDALM init.pp.
And because agents just automatically
grab packages to fix build errors,
it's spread like wildfire.
In just 46 minutes, 47,000 people downloaded it.
47,000.
And it exposed their AWS, their SSH keys,
their Docker secrets.
Just hoovered everything up.
So the industry is trying to fix this, right?
Clawed code just introduced this auto mode.
Right, where it uses separate model to check the work.
Yeah, it uses clause on it 4.6 in the background
to classify and block risky actions.
But my question is,
are we really relying on AI to protect us
from the code generated by other AI?
It's a completely flawed premise.
It feels like hiring a fox to guard the henhouse
just because this specific fox says he passed a security exam.
This raises an important question
about how these models actually work.
Non-deterministic AI safeguards are flawed
because prompt injection is real.
You can just trick the security guard.
Exactly, the AI looking for malware
can be tricked into ignoring it.
We still need deterministic sandboxes.
Hardtoded rules.
Right, like flies, sprites.dev or isolated-vm.
And we also need what package managers
like NPM, PNPM, and UV are doing now dependency cooldowns.
Oh, where they enforce a minimum release age
before a package can be automatically installed.
Exactly.
It's the only pragmatic human defense.
You have to force the automated systems to pause.
So if cloud-based agents are expensive,
they have all this overlapping functionality
and they pose these massive security risks,
the natural counter-movement for everyone listening
is bringing this power locally.
Getting off the cloud entirely.
Right.
And hardware economics right now are insane.
H100 GPU prices in the cloud are just melting up.
Elon Musk is building his Terrafab AI chip factory
just to keep up.
But locally, the open source community is absolutely thriving.
This is my favorite part of the briefing.
The breakthrough of streaming experts.
Tinker Dan Woods and a few others figured out
how to run these massive mixture of experts models
on consumer hardware.
It's a brilliant workaround.
Can you explain how this works?
Because they're basically streaming the necessary
neural weights directly from an SSD for each token, right?
Right.
A mixture of experts model doesn't use
its entire brain for every word.
It only uses specific experts.
So instead of loading the whole massive model into RAM,
which most laptops don't have enough of,
they just stream the tiny piece they need
from the hard drive at the exact millisecond they need it.
It's exactly like how Netflix changed everything.
Oh, that's a good comparison.
Yeah, like instead of waiting to download
a 50 gigabyte 4K movie before you can hit play,
you just stream the frames you need right now.
We are doing that with trillion parameter neural networks.
And the results are insane.
People are running the Keeney K2.5 model,
a 1 trillion parameter model
with 32 billion active weights running locally
on a 96 gigabyte M2 max MacBook Pro.
Which shouldn't be possible.
It shouldn't.
Another dev ran a massive Quinn 3.5 model right on an iPhone.
This completely decentralizes power.
You don't need a billion dollars or a huge server farm
to run frontier models anymore.
You could do it locally, securely, and completely privately.
Which completely changes the economics
for solo launch pernours.
You're not leaking your AWS keys
if your laptop is fully local and off the grid.
Exactly.
Well, we've covered a lot of ground today.
We explored the crazy reality
of remote control agents like Claude Dispatch.
We debated the financial savings
versus the cognitive debt of vibe coding.
The skyscraper analogy.
Right.
And we unpacked that terrifying LIDLM security breach
and found some serious hope in the streaming experts
running trillion parameter models on laptops.
To bring it all home, there's a quote from developer David Abram
in the sources that I think nails this.
He said, the machine didn't take your craft.
You gave it up.
Man, you gave it up.
LLMs don't understand the system.
They don't carry context.
And most importantly, they don't choose.
The real work of software development
is knowing what should exist in the first place and why.
So to you, listening, I want to leave you
with a final thought to mull over.
If AI agents completely removes the friction
of typing out code,
will the most valuable technical skill
in the year 2027 simply be the ability
to read and audit massive systems
rather than the ability to write them?
It's a totally different mindset.
It really is.
Thank you so much for joining us for this deep dive.
Check your dependencies, audit your subscriptions,
and we'll catch you next time.